Jaffrey, N.H. United Church of Jaffrey records, 1827-1980.
Congregational Library & Archives
Jaffrey, N.H. United Church of Jaffrey records, 1827-1980.
RG0106
Congregational Library & Archives
1.79 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
The roots of the United Church of Jaffrey start in 1850 when 23 members of Jaffrey's First Congregational Church established Jaffrey East Orthodox Congregational Church, erecting a meeting-house the same year. The United Church records document the history and life of the church, including reports, meeting minutes, vital statistics, financial information, church bulletins, auxiliary groups, correspondence, and property deeds. Records are fragmentary and incomplete.
East Congregational Church (Jaffrey, N.H.)
Federated Church (Jaffrey, N.H.)
First Baptist Church (Jaffrey, N.H.)
Universalist Church (Jaffrey, N.H.)
United Church of Jaffrey (Jaffrey, N.H.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Permanently loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives by The United Church of Jaffrey, June 1991; Acc# 1992-1.
Historical Note
The roots of the United Church of Jaffrey start in 1850 when 23 members of Jaffrey's First Congregational Church established Jaffrey East Orthodox Congregational Church, erecting a meeting-house the same year. The church built a parsonage and vestry in 1876. When the town's Universalist minister, Myron L. Cutler, died in 1930 the members of his church chose to join with East's congregation rather than find a new minister. The members of East also had connections with the Baptist church and still with First Congregational. Further inter-denominational ties were drawn when Jaffrey's Baptist minister, Roger Floyd, left his position in 1949. The small Baptist church chose to close rather than find a new minister; most of the members joined East. At this point, there were equal number of Baptists and Congregationalists, prompting a shift in name and organization. East Orthodox Church became the Federated Church with separate covenants for each denomination. In 1957 the Congregational members of the church voted to become a Covenant member of the New Hampshire Conference of the New Hampshire Conference of the United Church of Christ. After maintaining membership with both Baptist and UCC denominations, the members decided to withdraw from the Baptist Convention in 1970 to simplify day to day work as well as strengthen the bond as one United Church.
The Federated Church continued services in the old Baptist building, which was larger than the Congregational building. In 1959 the Federated Church dissolved its two components and formed the United Church of Jaffrey. Further building changes started in 1967. The old parish hall and parsonage were in disrepair. The current trend by mid-20th century was for ministers to live in their own house. This, plus the cost of restoration, meant the church chose to tear down the parsonage and old hall and build a new hall in 1970.
Ministers
East Congregational Church
John Edward Bullard Jewett 1850-1852
George Washington Adams 1854-1857
Franklin Dexter Austin 1858-1863
C.W. Allen 1863-1870
John C. Gowan 1870-1871
Darius Newton Goodrich 1872-1874
W. H. Dowden 1875-1880
John Calvin Staples 1880-1883
Ezra Jackson Riggs 1883-1886
Moses T. Runnells 1886-1889
Edward I. Ross 1890-1891
William H. Stuart 1891-1899
J. Sherman Grove 1899-1903
Millard Fillmore Hardy 1904-1910
David Howie 1911-1914
Charles G. Johnson 1915-1919
John H. Hoffman 1920-1922
Ambrose Jenkins 1923
Bruce W. Cronmiller 1924-1930
Henry Rees Jones 1930-1933
G. Gerald Parker 1933-1939
Levering Reynolds, Jr. 1939-1945
Richard Stoughton, Jr. 1945-1957
Federated Church
Byron Higgon 1957-1961
United Church
Interim Ministers 1961-1963
Mario Cestaro 1963-1969
United Church, UCC
Franklin L. Irvine 1969-1972
Emily B Preston 1972-1993
Lois Sundeen 1993-1995
William Beardslee 1995-2007
J.M. Shepherd 2007-2009
Teri Motley 2009-2014
Christopher C Owen 2014-2016
Mark Koyama 2016-present
Scope and Contents
The United Church records document the history and life of the church, including reports, meeting minutes, vital statistics, financial information, church bulletins, auxiliary groups, correspondence, and property deeds. Please be sure to read the history of the church and note both Universalist and Baptist church records are included from those extinct congregations. All series records are fragmentary and incomplete.
Arrangement
The collection has been organized into the five series listed below. Within each series, records have been arranged chronologically.
Series 1: First Baptist Church Records, 1827-1964
Series 2: East Congregational Church Records, 1849-1968
Series 3: First Universalist Society Records, 1875-1939
Series 4: Federated Church Records, 1949-1959
Series 5: United Church Records, 1956-1980
Related Materials
Cutter, Daniel B. History of the town of Jaffrey New Hampshire, from the date of the Masonian Charter to the present time, 1749-1880, Concord NH: Republican Press Association. 1881. (T J18.4C)
Gerould, Samuel L. The Congregational and Presbyterian Churches and Ministers of New Hampshire Connected With the General Association. Lebanon NH: H.E. Waite & Co. 1900. (9.3.67 (2))
Lawrence, Robert F. The New Hampshire Churches: comprising histories of the Congregational and Presbyterian churches in the state... Claremont Manufacturing Co. 1856. (9.3.36)
Livingston, W.W. and DeBevoise, G.H. Seventy Years of Cheshire Conference. Keene NH: Darling & Co. 1897. (9.6.37(1))
Bibliography
The United Church of Jaffrey, UCC. Celebrating 150 Years 1850-2000. Jaffrey: United Church of Jaffrey, U.C.C., 2000
Church membership.; Church newsletters.; Church records and registers.; Church societies.; Christian union.; Clergy -- Appointment, call, and election.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.).; Unitarian controversy.; East Congregational Church (Jaffrey, N.H.); Federated Church (Jaffrey, N.H.); First Baptist Church (Jaffrey, N.H.); Jaffrey (N.H.) -- Church history.; United Church of Jaffrey (Jaffrey, N.H.); Universalist Church (Jaffrey, N.H.)
- First Baptist Church records, 1827 1964; 1827-1964; 11 Files
  Historical Note
  The first meeting of the First Baptist Church in Jaffrey met on January 28, 1814. In 1823 the First Baptist Church & Society was formed and incorporated. After Rev. Roger Floyd departed in 1949, the Baptists voted to join in federation with the East Congregational Church, forming The Federated Church in Jeffrey. In 1959, after a decade of separate worship, the Congregationalists and Baptists joined fully and formed the United Church of Jaffrey.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes records from the extinct First Baptist Church in Jaffrey, NH. Types of records include: meeting minutes for several church societies; annual reports; letters of dismission; membership lists; property deeds.
  - Real estate deeds, 1827 1953; 1827-1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Baptist Female Benevolent Working Society minutes, 1844 1870; 1844-1870 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cheerful Workers minutes, 1878 1880; 1878-1880 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Charity Square minutes, 1883 1887; 1883-1887 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Charity Square minutes, 1888 1898; 1888-1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Charity Square minutes, 1898 1934; 1898-1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gold Gatherers minutes, 1895 1897; 1895-1897 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Women's Foreign Mission Society minutes, 1897 1920; 1897-1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - First Baptist Church, 1946 1959; 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Warrants, annual meeting minutes, reports, 1949 1958; 1949-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Yearly reports and conventions, 1949 1964; 1949-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- East Congregational Church records, 1849 1968; 1849-1968; 17 Files
  In 1850, 23 members of Jaffrey's First Congregational Church requested letters of dismission to begin a new Church in the increasingly populous eastern part of the town. That same year the East Congregational Church was built. 1876 saw an expansion of the church's property with the addition of a parsonage and vestry. In 1949, the Congregational and Baptist churches joined in Federation becoming the Federated Church of Jaffrey.
  This series includes records from the East Jaffrey Congregational Church in Jaffrey, NH. Types of records include: meeting minutes for several church societies; vital statistics; treasurer's records; correspondence; news clippings; property deeds; church letters; church histories; 1 photograph.
  - Deeds, 1849 1968; 1849-1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Register of vital statistics, 1875 1958; 1875-1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Society minutes, standing committee reports, 1882 1949; 1882-1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Loose papers and minutes, 1884 1946; 1884-1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 50th anniversary history, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Manuscript histories, 1899 1903; 1899-1903 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Junior Christian Endeavor minutes, 1902 1903; 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Junior Christian Endeavor minutes, 1904 1909; 1904-1909 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Memorial funds, bank book, and wills, 1903 1975; 1903-1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Documentation and receipts for church name change, 1919 1951; 1919-1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Repair fund ledgers, 1930 1940; 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - News clippings from The Recorder, 1934 1937; 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Monthly church letter, 1934 1939; 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Treasurer's ledger, 1934 1941; 1934-1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - George Gerald Parker papers, 1935 1939; 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Special funds and endowment lists, 1935 1958; 1935-1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Edward I. Ross photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- First Universalist Society records, 1875 1939; 1875-1939; 2 Files
  The First Universalist Society of Jaffrey was started in 1822 and the Society was incorporated as a religious corporate body in 1875. The death of Rev. Myron L. Cutler in 1930, after serving his church for 43 years, became the impetus for the small congregation to close permanently with many of its members joining East Congregational Church and smaller numbers joining both the Baptist Church and First Church.
  This series includes records from the extinct First Universalist Society in Jaffrey, NH. Types of records include: yearbooks; annual meeting reports; trustees reports; treasurer's and collector's reports; sales receipts; church histories.
  - First Universalist Society records, 1901 1939; 1901-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - First Universalist Society records, 1875 1938; 1875-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Federated Church records, 1949 1959; 1949-1959; 8 Files
  The Federated Church of Jaffrey formed in 1949 after the First Baptist Church and the East Jaffrey Congregational Church joined in federation. The two denominations maintained separate worship and Covenants with the New Hampshire Baptist Convention and New Hampshire Conference of Congregational-Christian Churches. Worship was held at the Federated Church while the Baptist Church at Charity Square became the new Parish Hall and center of church-related activities. In 1959, at the recommendation of the Rev. Richard Stoughton, Jr., the two member churches of the Federated Church dissolved and together formed the United Church of Jaffrey.
  This series includes records from the Federated Church in Jaffrey, NH. Types of records include: meeting minutes for several church societies; annual meeting minutes; church correspondence; Sunday calendars; religious histories; sermon.
  - Articles of agreement, amendments, and incorporation, 1949 1958; 1949-1958 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Federated guild minutes, 1950 1955; 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Annual meetings, 1951 1959; 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The Spire, 1953 1958; 1953-1958 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Historical items, 1956 1958; 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Ministerial search correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Federated church records, 1957 1959; 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Deacons/deaconesses meeting minutes, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- United Church records, 1956 1980; 1956-1980; 17 Files
  The United Church of Jaffrey formed out of the Federated Church in 1959, when the East Congregational Church and First Baptist Church dissolved to form into a single church body. The United Church of Jaffrey is a member of the United Church of Christ and continues to serve its community today.
  This series includes records from The United Church in Jaffrey, NH. Types of records include: meeting minutes for several church societies; annual meeting minutes; deeds; building records; news clippings; newsletters; membership lists; constitution.
  - Newsletters, bulletins, and newspaper clippings, 1956-1976 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Proposals to unite, constitution, and by-laws, 1958 1970; 1958-1970 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Deeds, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Register of vital statistics, 1959 1963; 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Vital statistics, 1959 1979; 1959-1979 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Vital statistics, 1962 1969; 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Annual meetings, 1959 1963; 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Annual meetings, 1964 1971; 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Annual meetings, 1972 1976; 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Children's choir awards, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Building alterations, programs and news clippings, 1960 1970; 1960-1970 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Parish house specifications, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Membership directories, 1962 1978; 1962-1978 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Council minutes, 1968 1971; 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Council minutes, 1972 1973; 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Council minutes, 1974 1978; 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Council minutes, 1979 1980; 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 50)